John Alan Sha paddles through the Indian
Ocean.
He's on a holy mission sent from God. As
he nears the shore, he spots them. They
are shouting at him in a language he
doesn't understand.
He carefully listens to the sounds they
make. In an attempt to greet them, he
responds by imitating the sounds, their
laugh.
Then two come towards him. So he throws
gifts wrapped around two large fish into
the shallow water. Then he starts to
sing Christian worship songs. And for a
moment they pause.
>> But his kayak scrapes onto the dead
coral, forcing him to get out. And some
of them are getting very close now.
Suddenly a child grabs an arrow, pulls
back his bow, and shoots.
John entered a forbidden place where
time stands still. Outsiders like him
are not welcome. North Sentinel Island
is one of the most secluded places on
Earth. And it's home to a tribe that has
lived in total isolation for tens of
thousands of years.
We don't know what language they speak,
how many they are, or even what they
call themselves. Over the years, contact
attempts have ended in confusion,
violence, and death. Myths, viral
headlines, and speculation have turned
North Sentinel into a modern-day
internet legend. The real story is much
more nuanced.
It's one of intrusive American tourists
with diet cokes, ruthless Christian
missionaries, abusive colonialists,
traumatized children, and a highly
destructive obsession with the exotic.
[Music]
The internet has a lot to say about
North Sentinel Island.
>> They have a theory that North Sentinel
Island is home to a top secret research
facility.
>> There is an island in the Andaman chain
called North Sentinel Island. They kill
everybody who lands there essentially.
What really caught my eye was this
circular building, three little
offshoots coming off of it. There's
North Sentinel merch, Instagram pages,
and fake Google reviews. Most of all,
it's known for being dangerous.
[Music]
North Sentinel has become a meme. In
January 2025, this American YouTuber
entered the island. He filmed himself
trying to make contact with the
Sentinel. As a peace offering, he left
behind a can of Diet Coke, but he never
actually made contact. Instead, he got
arrested. Indian police are currently
investigating him for illegally
trespassing in the strictly forbidden
zone. He is likely facing up to 5 years
in prison.
>> I think we live in a world where all we
need to do is sort of flip open our
laptop or um look at our phone and we
can connect with just about anybody in
the world, learn anything that we want
to learn, see any place that we want to
see. And yet there's still this one
place that's isolated. So, it really is
kind of the last place in some ways
that's unexplored on our planet.
>> North Sentinel is not what the internet
paints it to be. To truly grasp it, we
need to go back in time, quite far back.
It's the last ice age. A group of early
humans set up from their home in Africa.
It's still debated when exactly that
took place, but it is believed to be
between 40 and 60,000 years ago. They're
among the first to migrate eastward
across the vast Asian continent in
search of more favorable climates, new
food sources, and habitable land. The
world looks very different. Massive ice
sheets cover parts of North America and
Europe. Since much of Earth's water is
locked in ice, sea levels are often far
lower than they are today. What we now
call the Asian continent stretches
farther. Some islands are connected and
so these early humans walk. They cross
landscapes long lost beneath the waves
of what we now call the Indian Ocean.
They likely use vessels like rafts or
canoes to hop from island to island. And
their journey eventually brings them
here. We don't know when, possibly up to
50,000 years ago. Today it's the
Anderman Archipelago nestled in the Bay
of Bengal. As thousands of years pass
and the glaciers melt, the sea levels
slowly rise. Bit by bit, their world
shrinks
and what ultimately remains is a single
remote island roughly the size of
Manhattan. North Sentinel.
We spend countless hours crafting these
animations, researching, building,
refining, all to tell stories that
matter. Maybe you're building something,
too. A product, a brand, a business.
That's where Shopify comes in. Shopify
is a powerful all-in-one platform. We've
personally used it for years for our
sustainable clothing business. We've
built a professional online shop with
ease, constantly optimizing the user
experience. Beyond core features like
useful analytics and life views, Shopify
offers two great new tools. Horizon
makes designing your store even easier.
You pick the theme, then customize the
layout however you like. It's fast,
smooth, and easy to use. Sidekick looks
at your store's data in real time and
offers useful insights. what's working,
what's not, and what to try next. So, if
you are thinking of starting something
or just want a better way to run it, try
Shopify for free at shopify.com/fern or
scan this QR code.
The exact origin of North Sentinel's
population is still a mystery. No
genetic material has ever been collected
from the Sentinel, but the DNA of
neighboring Andermanise tribes has been
studied. The Eni and Jarava are believed
to be closely related to the Sentineles.
Scientists found that their genes carry
two rare variants not found in mainland
India populations. They are totally
unique to the Andes.
That means they likely split off from
other human populations very early on
between 25 and 42,000 years ago.
Genetically, the Sentinel are likely one
of the most unique human tribes on
Earth, which also makes them one of the
most vulnerable ones.
This is John, 2 years before his journey
to North Sentinel Island. He's 24 years
old, raised in a Christian household. He
went to an evangelical high school, just
like his father. He's known for two
passions, the outdoors and Jesus Christ.
John is deeply interested in missionary
work.
Though his parents are Christian as
well, they don't share his enthusiasm,
especially his father. But Jon seems to
genuinely enjoy immersing himself in
evangelical doctrine. Right now, he's
browsing through the Joshua Project.
That's a Christian missionary database
which tracks so-called unreached people
groups.
One entry is about North Sentinel.
Sentinel people need to know that the
creator god exists and that he loves
them and paid the price for their sins.
We don't know much about the Sentinel.
The entire population is possibly
somewhere between 80 and 100 people.
Their language remains a complete
mystery. No one, not even neighboring
tribes, can understand it. No one knows
what they call themselves. They live in
small huts grouped tightly together.
Overall, they're quite crafty. wooden
buckets, bows, arrows, all self-made
with raw materials from the island. In
the jungle, they hunt pigs. Along the
reefs, they fish. They also eat local
fruits and raw honey. The Sentinel are
taller, more muscular, and overall
healthier than their neighbors.
A tsunami wre havoc in the region in
2004, but the Sentinel miraculously
survived. Experts believe this may have
to do with their indigenous knowledge
system. Foresight and wisdom is passed
down from generation to generation. But
this was perhaps the strangest discovery
in a Sentinel village. A wooden board
about 52 by 30 cm big with 64
alternating squares. It looks exactly
like a chess board. Did the Sentineles
carve it themselves or did it wash up
from the sea? No one knows. No other
Anderman shribe has ever shown evidence
of playing games like chess.
John has been obsessed with the
Sentineles for years now. The missionary
website advises so-called prayer points.
Pray that the Indian government will
allow Christians to earn the trust of
the Sentineles people and that they will
be permitted to live among them. Pray
that God will open doors to Sentinel
people to receive the gospel message.
John could be the first one that brings
Christianity to them. In fact, he thinks
it's his calling.
>> God, I thank you for choosing me before
I was even yet formed in my mother's
womb to be your messenger of your great
news to the people of North Sentinel
Island.
The Sentinel certainly didn't express
any desire to be converted. Their
experience with intruders has been,
well, pretty terrible.
It's the year 1880. A Sentineel family
walks through the jungle. Suddenly, they
hear voices through the bushes.
Unfamiliar voices.
>> For weeks now, strange white men have
been fighting their way through the
jungle on the island. They carry weapons
and seem to be looking for inhabitants.
When they approached one of their
villages some days earlier, the Sentinel
ran away. Now, suddenly, they stand face
to face. Ready to defend his family. The
old man reaches for an arrow. The armed
intruders rapidly encircle the Sentinel
family.
They are led by the man in the center.
His name is Moras Vidal Portman, and
he's been searching for them for a long
time.
Portman is a 20-year-old British officer
put in charge to oversee the Andaman
Islands under colonial rule. He is
fascinated with the indigenous tribes in
the area. While staying in Port Blair,
the capital city of the Andaman Islands,
he immersed himself in the study of the
Andes people, culture, food, crafts, and
tattoos. Everything is carefully
documented in his notebooks. He arranges
young and men for the camera, posing
them in unnatural, almost performative
ways. He likes to surround himself with
a group of Andes convict servants. He
calls them junglies.
But there's one place he hasn't
conquered so far. North Sentinel
Islands. To him, it's the last great
mystery of the archipelago. He's
obsessed with the Sentinel, convinced
that he could be the first white man
they'll ever meet. He's tried to contact
them before and failed. But now he has a
new plan. As the old Sentineles man
draws his arrow, one of the intruders
jumps on his back. The three
Sentineelles have wrestled down and
taken, torn from the only home they've
ever known. Portman has been brought
back to his ship. Three Sentineles
children are already on board. Captured
earlier, the islanders don't understand
who these men are or what they want.
Portman takes them back to Port Blair.
Here, he keeps them at his house to
study them closer. The Sentinel become
very sick right away. Within just a few
days, the old man and the woman die.
Most likely, they were exposed to
microbes and diseases their immune
system couldn't handle. Now, it's just
the four Sentinel children without the
elders. A few days later, they're sent
back to the island, overloaded with
gifts. Portman hopes they'll return to
their people as willing ambassadors.
The children might have carried the very
microbes that killed the men and the
woman. We don't know what happened to
them afterwards.
Infections remain one of the greatest
dangers to isolated tribes. Many have
never been exposed to common viruses
like the flu or even a cold. Their
immune system simply can't cope. What's
harmless to the rest of the world could
be deadly for them. A single infection
from an outsider could wipe out an
entire tribe. In the 16th century,
Spanish colonizers brought diseases to
South America, likely without realizing
it. In some regions, entire populations
were cut in half. Andaman tribes were
affected by this too. The Ang and Jarava
have seen a dramatic collapse in their
population. In 1901, the Eni numbered
around 670. Today, barely 100 remain.
Colonial intrusion, infectious diseases,
and the steady loss of their land have
all played a role in their decline. And
Portman himself played a crucial role.
According to historian Adam Goodhart, he
was
>> very much a participant um in and at
least complicit with the genocide
against the Andaman Islanders that was
committed by the British in the 1800s.
Um somebody who was involved in
exploitation including sexual
exploitation and physical abuse of the
native people. And really if it had been
up to Portman, it probably would have
happened to the Sentinel as well because
he tried repeatedly to invade the island
as he had done um with many other groups
and to bring them into submission to
British rule.
>> Years later, Portman himself would admit
that his actions may have sealed a
Sentinel distrust of outsiders for good.
John finds himself blindfolded on a dirt
road somewhere in the state of Kansas.
He was put there and left alone. In the
woods nearby, he finds a village. The
inhabitants of the village appear to be
some kind of native tribe, but not
really. The village is fake and the
inhabitants are actors with costumes.
All of this is part of his training.
John joined a secretive boot camp for
Christian missionaries. All Nations is a
religious organization that trains
people like John for their quests. And
he is right in the middle of an
exercise. His task is to preach the
teachings of Jesus to the isolated tribe
he considers unholy heathens. The fake
village people act as if they're
hostile, aggressively threatening him
with fake spears, speaking gibberish. To
Jon, this is the ultimate test that will
prepare him for his big mission on North
Sentinel. He knows the danger of setting
foot on the island. He knows it could
cost him his life.
In 1974, a National Geographic film crew
tried to meet Sentineles face to face on
camera for the first time. The
Sentineles spotted the boat from afar
and waved their arms, mocked the
outsiders, and shot arrows at the crew.
They clearly did not want visitors.
7 years later, a cargo ship named
Primrose ran a ground on a reef on North
Sentinel during a terrible storm. At
first, the crew was probably relieved to
be near dry land. But just 2 days later,
they sent a desperate cable. Wild men
estimate more than 50 carrying various
homemade weapons are making two or three
wooden boats, worrying they will board
us at sunset or crew members lives not
guaranteed. But because of the weather
conditions, rescue missions failed. So
the crew had to guard the ship with a
flare gun, axes, and some lengths of
pipe. But before it got to an actual
fight, the crew was finally evacuated by
helicopter.
But still, Jon is determined to go. To
him, North Sentinel may be Satan's last
stronghold, and he could be their
savior. I think I might die tomorrow and
I wish I could have had more time to
express my thanks to you.
Now Jon is out of his kayak and an arrow
is fired at him. Miraculously, it only
pierces his Bible. He's unharmed. At
least according to John's diary. It's
unclear if his Bible actually saved him.
It could well have been a bit of
storytelling on his side. What's clear,
the Sentinel chase him into the water.
In panic, he swims away towards a boat
out at sea. It belongs to local Indian
fishermen. Before setting off for North
Sentinel Island, Jon had paid the
fisherman a $325 bribe to take him
there. They departed from Port Blair,
towing a kayak behind it, the one Jon
would use to make his approach to the
island.
Back on the boat, Jon takes stock of the
situation. His Pelican case is gone. He
had to leave it behind when he fled. It
included a first aid kit, clothes, other
essentials, and his passport. He had
previously hidden another case on shore
when he first landed to scout out the
cove in the early morning. It is unknown
if the Sentinel found both cases,
especially the one he hid might still be
there to this day. Without his passport,
he can't easily travel back to the US.
For Jon, it's just another reason to
stay and pursue his mission further. But
the Sentinel made it very clear. They do
not want him there. And Jon really
doesn't want to die. Yet, he decides to
give it another try. You guys might
think I'm crazy in all this, but I think
it's worth it to declare Jesus to these
people. Please do not be angry at them
or at God if I get killed. Don't
retrieve my body. Sully De Gloria, John
Cow. November 16th, 2018.
6:20 in the morning.
The next day, John takes the supposed
Pierced Bible as a sign. Today, he
believes is the day he will start to
bring Jesus to the Sentinel.
This time, he tells the fishermen to
leave without him. Next, he strips down
to his underpants in an attempt to gain
the trib's trust. Then, he steps back
into the water and starts swimming.
The island is just within reach.
There are no records of what exactly
happened that day. The only thing we
know for sure is the outcome.
One day passes. The fishermen return and
look for Jon. He's nowhere to be seen.
Then suddenly they spot something.
A group of Sentinel emerge from the
treeine, dragging Jon's dead body across
the sand. No words, no mercy. The
message is clear. He crossed a line he
was never meant to cross.
John Ellen Chow's death in 2018 made
global news. Some called him a dumb
American, a deluded idiot. John's
father, a Christian himself, doesn't
share this view. He blames evangelicals
extreme Christianity for his son's
death. In an email to the Guardian, he
called religion the opium of the masses.
The evangelical organization that
trained him depicted John as a martyr.
In a statement, they said, "The
privilege of sharing the gospel has
often involved great cost."
A long time ago, a group of scientists
actually managed to make peaceful
contact with the Sentinel after decades
of trying. But these same scientists
eventually pushed for the island to be
under India's protection. Driven by
concerns for the trib's health, the
island has been off limits since the
late '90s. All anthropological work
stopped. No more expeditions, no more
gifts, no more visits. And to us, that's
a good thing. After all, the North
Sentinel never asked for any of this.
[Music]